

(+1) 847-641-0586 <u>kaiyuhou2022@u.northwestern.edu</u> <u>www.kyhou.com</u> 1111 Church St. Apt. 605 Evanston, IL, 60201

I am currently a fourth year Ph.D. candidate in the Computer Science Department at Northwestern University, advised by Prof. Yan Chen. I have a broad interest in various aspects of cloud networks and network protocols. My current research focuses on network optimization of microservices/serverless based cloud. I am also working for introducing formal methods into network protocol verification.

#### **Education**

## Ph.D. Student in Computer Science Northwestern University

2017 - (2022)

Evanston, IL

- Advisor: Prof. Yan Chen

- Area: Networked System, Cloud Networking

- GPA: 3.97/4.0

## Master's in Computer Science Xi'an Jiaotong University

2014 - 2017

Shaanxi, China

- Advisor: Prof. Chengchen Hu

- Area: Software Defined Networking (SDN)

- Rank: 1st/89 GPA: 3.81/4.0 Average: 91.7

# • B.E. in Software Engineering Xi'an Jiaotong University

2010 - 2014

Shaanxi, China

- Rank: 1st/78 GPA: 3.94/4.0 Average: 92.4 (in Junior and Senior year)

### **Work Experiences**

• SRI International

Menlo Park, CA

Research Intern, at Computer Science Laboratory

Jun. 2020 - Sep. 2020

- Advisor: Dr. Vinod Yegneswaran
- Designed and implemented an enterprise-wide radio situational awareness system

#### Research: Cloud Networks & SDN

• **Network Optimizing for Microservices-based Cloud** (work in progress)

2020 - Present

- Microservice/serverless architecture brings flexibility but introduces network communication delay
- Aim to integrate the **QUIC protocol** into **Kubernetes** to replace the slow https calls
- Aim to design systematic metrics to provide a benchmark for the microservice network performance
- Working on integrating QUIC into GRPC and **OpenFaaS** to improve serverless platform performance

#### • Generic Security Policy Enforcement System for SDN-based Cloud

2017 - 2018

- Designed a **policy language** for resource protection and management of SDN-based Cloud
- Implemented in the OpenDaylight controller, and deployed on OpenStack

**Publication**: [IWQoS'18] Lightweight Resource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud

- Routing Policy for Solving Reactive Model Overhead of Software Defined Networks 2016 2017
  - Proposed a routing policy to reduce the control channel bandwidth consumption up to 80%
  - Implemented in the Floodlight controller under the OpenFlow protocol with Open vSwitch
  - Deployed on the ONetSwitch, an OpenFlow white-box switch with Xilinx FPGA

**Publication**: [ICNP'17] SoftRing: Taming the reactive model for software defined networks

#### Research: Formal Methods for Network Protocols

• Formal Verification and Vulnerability Detection of LTE/5G Protocols

2019 - 2020

- Used **TLA+** to formally specify the emergency call systems in **4G/5G** cellular network protocols
- Built a complete cellular network testbed (USRP, OpenAirInterface) and verified these issues
- Discovered serious availability and security issues in real-world, acknowledged by major carriers

Publication: [Under Review] Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods

- Formal Safe Configuration Search for Network Protocols (work in progress) 2
  - Traditionally, researchers use safe properties to verify a protocol is safe or find counterexamples
  - We convert this decision problem into a search problem. Given the model and the properties, we aim to search the boundaries of the configuration space where the system is always secure and reliable.
  - We employ inductive generalization and improved IC3 algorithm to determine the space.

**Publication**: [Sigcomm'20 Poster] Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot

#### **Publication List**

- Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods
   Kaiyu Hou\*, You Li\*, Yinbo Yu, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (\*equal contribution)
   Under Review
- Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot
  You Li\*, Kaiyu Hou\*, Hai Zhou, Yan Chen (\*equal contribution)
  ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication (SIGCOMM, Poster), 2020.
- State of the Art and Research Challenges in the Security Technologies of Network Function Virtualization
  Xiaochun Wu, Kaiyu Hou, Xue Leng, Xing Li, Yinbo Yu, Bo Wu, Yan Chen
  IEEE Internet Computing, 2020
- CellScope: Automatically Specifying and Verifying Cellular Network Protocols
   Yinbo Yu, You Li, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou, Jianfeng Yang

   ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication (SIGCOMM, Poster), 2019

- A Lightweight Policy Enforcement System for Resource Protection and Management in the SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song, You Li Computer Networks, Elsevier, 2019
- *COIN: A fast packet inspection method over compressed traffic*Xiuwen Sun, Hao Li, Dan Zhao, Xingxing Lu, **Kaiyu Hou**, Chengchen Hu
  Journal of Network and Computer Applications, Elsevier, 2019
- SDNKeeper: Lightweight Recource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song IEEE/ACM 26th International Symposium on Quality of Service (IWQoS), 2018
- SoftRing: Taming the reactive model for software defined networks
   Chengchen Hu, Kaiyu Hou (1st student author), Hao Li, Ruilong Wang, Peng Zheng, Peng Zhang,
   Huanzhao Wang
   IEEE 25th International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), 2017
- Towards A Fast Packet Inspection over Compressed HTTP Traffic
  Xiuwen Sun, Kaiyu Hou, Hao Li, Chengchen Hu
  IEEE/ACM 25th International Symposium on Quality of Service (IWQoS), 2017

## Teaching Experiences

| • | CS 214: Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University                                   | Winter, 2021 |
|---|--|--------------|
| • | CS 214: Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University                                   | Fall, 2020   |
| • | CS 212, Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University                         | Spring, 2020 |
| • | CS 340, Introduction to Networking ( <b>Best Teaching Assistant Award</b> )  Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University | Winter, 2020 |
| • | CS 214, Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University                                   | Fall, 2019   |
| • | EECS 343, Operating Systems  Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University   | Spring, 2019 |
| • | EECS 340, Introduction to Networking Assistant Lecturer, Northwestern University   | Winter, 2019 |
| • | EECS 340, Introduction to Networking Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University   | Fall, 2018   |
| • | IT 458, Information Security and Assurance Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University                                   | Winter, 2018 |

• Computer Programming (C++) for CS Honored Class Teaching Assistant, Xi'an Jiaotong University

Fall, 2016

# **Professional Services**

- Sub-reviewer of ACM CCS (2018, 2019)
- Sub-reviewer of IEEE ICDCS (2018)
- Reviewer of IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN)

# Awards

| Tivarab  |                  |
|--|------------------|
| Bronze Medal, ACM-ICPC Asia Regional Contest   | 2012, 2013, 2014 |
| Silver Medal, ACM-ICPC China Province Contest, Chengdu   | 2012, 2013       |
| • Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM)   | 2013             |
| Honor  |                  |
| • <b>Best Teaching Assistant Award</b> ( <i>Peter and Adrienne Barris</i> Outstanding TA) <i>Northwestern University</i> | 2020             |
| • Graduate (Cadre) with Honor  Xi'an Jiaotong University   | 2017             |
| • Excellent Postgraduate Student Leader Award Xi'an Jiaotong University  | 2015, 2016       |
| • Graduate with Honor Xi'an Jiaotong University  | 2014             |
| • Excellent Student Model Nomination (16/13000)  Xi'an Jiaotong University   | 2013             |
| • Google Excellence Scholarship  Awarded to 3 students from each of 20 top Chinese universities                          | 2013             |
| • Excellent Student Award Xi'an Jiaotong University  | 2011, 2012, 2013 |
| Social Activities  |                  |
| • <b>Student President</b> of Computer Science Dept., (Class 2017) <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>                      | 2014 - 2017      |
| • <b>Student Councilor</b> , the Student Congress of ChungYing College <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>                  | 2013 - 2014      |
| • Chair, the ACM-ICPC Club  Xi'an Jiaotong University  | 2012 - 2013      |

| • | Science and Education Minister of Student Union              | 2011-2012 |
|---|--|-----------|
|   | Xi'an Jiaotong University                                    |           |
| • | Co-Founder & the 2 <sup>nd</sup> Store Manager of Bingo Cafe | 2010-2013 |
|   | ChungYing College, Xi'an Jiaotong University                 |           |

# Skills

- L2/L3/L4 Protocols, 3GPP Cellular Network Protocols (NAS layer), 802.11 Protocols
- Microservice Networks, Serverless Platforms, Cloud Networks, SDN
- Formal Methods for Network Protocols
- Python, Go-lang